When we look at the landscape globally,
we see two dominant players, China and
the US, way ahead of everybody else. And
then we have the middle countries,
there's about 10 of us together. And
really affording what China and the US
has built without collaborative
innovation would be impossible. When we
saw the first LLMs being opened up in
2023, first of all with the Llama leak
and then Llama opening up in the July,
what we saw was a pace of innovation
that was really unprecedented, right?
One of the big values of something being
open is iterative development,
innovators being able to freely access
and use technology they wouldn't
otherwise have access to, and to build
on top of it. And you see that shift
from Meta with Llama through to Deep
Seek with R1.
You mentioned the Meta and Llama there.
Now Now Meta stated that Llama's open
source. The Linux Foundation backed them
up. You called them out. So in July '23,
we were actually Open UK was the only
organization that supported the launch
of Llama as open innovation. Mhm. And it
was very carefully structured all the
way through, I think it was 23rd of July
off the top of my head, to that date as
open innovation because the license has
two things. It has an acceptable use for
policy that puts restrictions in.
And it has a commercialization provision
that says when you hit X million users,
you have to go back and get a commercial
license from Meta.
>> Mhm. Nobody knows what the the terms of
that license is cuz I don't think
anybody's hit that level of use that's
been trackable Mhm. to date.
So what that means is when you go back
to that basic principle of open source,
that anyone can use it for any purpose,
that just doesn't happen, right? You've
always got the risk of this restriction.
You don't have that same free flow, that
ability to cascade the outputs and let
somebody else use it, iterate it, and
build on top of it. So that that's kind
of broken. And it was fine as open
innovation, and we supported it, and I
still think it's the right thing to do
because that shift opening up an LLM was
critical for change in the industry, and
I think it will go down in history as
one of the seminal moments.
If you talk to people today about Llama
and Meta, they'll say to you that the
word on the street is they're moving
away from openness.
And I think it's because they haven't
done it right. They haven't actually
created true open source. So, they they
themselves weren't calling it until open
source until Zuck posted on Facebook.
And by that point, you know, nobody was
going to go backwards from there.
Whether it was intentional or not, we'll
never know unless he tells us, of
course. Now, DeepSeek was a model that
was, I think, it's a distilled model for
Yeah, R1 open. R1 R1, not R1 open, yes.
>> Yeah. And And so, first of all, what is
a distilled model?
Yes, so they took Qwen and they took
Llama and used what was in there through
this distillation technique to create
something equivalent without actually
building a model from scratch. And that
was super impactful because it took the
price of building a model down
apparently to 5 million instead of 100
million, right? So, 5% of the the cost
at that point in time.
I think that that distillation was
really huge in terms of the innovation
for the time. So, I had quite an
interesting experience in December. I
went out to China I several years ago,
and I edited a book in on open source
law.
And it's been translated by Chinese open
source community into Mandarin.
It's a 640-page long book, so it took a
bit of time to do it. And I was really
lucky to get a a call with DeepSeek when
I was there, and I'm not allowed to
discuss the contents specifically,
but it was an interesting experience,
and it was interesting not just to talk
to them, but to talk to people across
the marketplace there.
And you know, like,
DeepSeek's obviously big, Qwen and
Kimmy, but Kimmy seemed to be the thing
that absolutely every developer was
using in China.
>> Interesting.
>> really seemed to be running ahead for
the developers. Yeah. Yeah. And And
that's interesting with Kimmy because
there were rumors, I think, on either
Reddit or or Hacker News, that Kimmy was
actually uh the the core model behind uh
Cursor's Composer 2 model, which was
just recently released. And there was a
uh I don't know if it was trolling. I
don't know if how much truth there is,
but it's very interesting that I think
more and more of uh developers are
becoming uh
it's becoming it's becoming clearer to
developers that not every model is built
from scratch. And different models are
learning from each other. Absolutely.
>> Yeah, it has to be. It really has to be.
So So, what time uh do you think it
makes sense for a developer to use uh
you know an an expensive model, maybe an
Opus or something from uh from OpenAI,
versus that you know the cheaper model,
you know, these models that are derived
from each other? Because the costs are
so low, they're naturally going to be
cheaper to the end user. So, at what
stage does it does the does a developer
need to make that decision? I think
we're in an odd position right now where
when we look at uptake and adoption, it
is actually much lower now than you
would expect it to be in the open-source
front.
And it's very reminiscent of open-source
software sort of 20 years ago.
And I think a lot of it is for similar
reasons, which were about risk
management, lack of understanding, you
know, maybe unnecessary fears, not
really knowing what what the the
consequence of of it being open were
going to be. And I think what we saw
then was risk professionals, lawyers,
procurement, finance, who had to sign
off on contracts saying no.
And then there was sort of a shift and a
momentum gathering around GitHub. And I
think what we will see, it won't be a
decision about a specific engineer or
developer making a decision to use it,
is we'll see an industry shift where it
just becomes the norm. And I think it's
an absolute inevitability.
And I'm reassured by hearing people like
Yann LeCun saying the same thing, you
know, at events I've been at in the last
few weeks. I I just think there is no
way round it, particularly for anybody
who is not from the US or China. And of
course, if you're from China, you're
already probably using open models.